A Guide to the Judith Edelman Architectural Papers, 1947-2009
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Judith Edelman Architectural Papers 1948-2009
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Edelman, Judith, 1923-2014;
Ms1997-010
0.5 cu. ft., 3 boxes
Judith Edelman was a partner at The Edelman Partnership/Architects of New York City, and is a founding member of the Alliance of Women in Architecture (AWA) and Fellow of the American Institute of Architects. Her papers consist of newspaper clippings, correspondence, writings, and published literature about Edelman's activities with the AWA, as well as writings about her work as an advocate for women in the field of architecture. They also include photographs, floorplans, and supplementary information about seven architectural projects done by her.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Judith Edelman Architectural Papers were donated to the International Archive of Women in Architecture by their creator in January 1997. Additional materials were donated by the creator in June 1997 and by Edelman's estate in March 2015.
Scope and Content
The Judith Edelman papers consist of newspaper clippings, correspondence, drafts of lectures, and published writings by Edelman and others, and photographs and other information about selected architectural projects done by Edelman. The collection contains information about Edelman's activities with the Alliance of Women in Architecture, as well as writings by her and about her work as an advocate for women in the field of architecture. There is correspondence and other materials related to the AIA exhibit "That Exceptional One: Women in American Architecture, 1888-1988."
The collection also includes information about seven architectural projects done by Edelman from 1967 to 1992, with photographs, floor plans, and supplementary material describing the projects.
Biographical/Historical Information
Judith Edelman (nee Hochberg) was born on September 16, 1923, in Brooklyn, New York. She was educated at Connecticut College (1940-41), New York University (1941-42), and Columbia University School of Architecture (1942-46) where she received her B. Arch. in 1946. She apprenticed with architect Huson Jackson from 1948 to 1958, then worked for architect Harold Edelman from 1958 to 1960 and as a designer for Edelman & Salzman from 1960 to 1964. She was a partner in Edelman & Salzman, Architects, from 1964 to 1978, and The Edelman Partnership/Architects in New York City from 1979 to the present. She is a registered architect in New York.
Edelman served as chairwoman of the Task Force on Women in Architecture for the American Institute of Architects (AIA) from 1974 to 1975. She was awarded a fellowship in the AIA in 1981. She was designated a "Woman of Vision" in 1989 from the National Organization for Women and is a founding member of the Alliance of Women in Architecture and a member of the International Union of Women Architects.
Sources:
Martin, D. (2014, October 18). "Judith Edelman, Architect, 91, Is Dead; Firebrand in a Male-Dominated Field". New York Times.
https://www.nytimes.com/2014/10/19/business/judith-edelman-architect-91-is-dead-firebrand-in-a-male-dominated-field.html
Arrangement
The collection is divided into two series.
Series I contains clippings, correspondence, and writings by and about Edelman arranged by topic.
Series II includes photographs, floors plans, and other material relating to seven of Edelman's projects arranged chronologically.
Index Terms
Persons:
Edelman, Judith, 1923-2014
Subjects:
International Archive of Women in Architecture; History of Women in Architecture; Women-owned architectural firms; Women architects -- New York
- Series I: Personal
  - Biographical Information, 1997-1998, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Profiles and interviews with Edelman, 1973-1982, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Personal correspondence, 1947, 1973, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Family portrait (color); black and white photographs, c. 1970s, probably taken by Robert Ipcar for "What Can She Be? An Architect."
- Series II: Professional
  - Subseries A: Writings
    - Review of 'Housing Messages,' Journal of architectural research (vol 7 No 3), August 1980 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "Barriers to Architectural Innovation: The Case of Two Bridges," by Edelman, published as a chapter in The Unsheltered Woman, edited by Eugenie Ladner Birch 1985 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Memo, women in architectural program at Columbia University (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Subseries B: Presentations and lectures
    - Speech draft, SHF Annual Meeting, 9 June 1983 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Rensselaer Polytechnic Institute, Lecture Series (poster), 1977-1978 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Claire Watsun Forrest Memorial Lecture Series at the School of Architecture and Allied Arts at the University of Oregon, with two interviews with Edelman 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Hunter College, Women and Housing Seminar 1981-1983 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Subseries C: Associations and Committees
    - American Institute of Architects, women in architecture, 1973-1989 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Includes copy of the 1975 AIA Affirmative Action Plan and documents from the Task Force on Women in Architecture, chaired by Edelman.
    - Organization of Women Architects and Design Professionals, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - New York State Association of Architects, 1973 Convention (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - American Institute of Architects, New York Chapter, 1971-1979, 2009 (Honors Committee) (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - National Organization for Women, New York Chapter, 1989 and 2008 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      Includes correspondence and acceptance speech draft 1989 Women of Vision Award.
  - Subseries D: Conferences and Travel
    - Women in Architecture Symposium, Washington University, 29 March 1974 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - West Coast Women's Design Conference, University of Oregon, 18-20 April 1974 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Conference for Women in Design and Planning, Boston Architectural Center, 7-9 November 1975 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - China Study Group on Environmental Issues, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Urban Poverty and Distributive Justice, New York, NY, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - American Academy of Rome, Rome Prize Fellowship Application, 1990-1991 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Preservation League of NYC, Cuba 2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Cuba, 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - American Academy of Rome, 27 October - 10 November 2003 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Subseries E: Exhibitions
    - NYC-AIA Exhibition, 'Women in Architecture,' 1974 (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - 'Alliance of Women in Architecture, 1972-1982', 1982 (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence Re: American Institute of Architects,'That Exceptional One,1987-1988' (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - AIA/NYChapter, 'Projections: A Celebration of Work by Women,' 1996 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Subseries F: Reference files
    - Women in Architecture,' Architectural Forum, September 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Making Room: Women and Architecture,' Heresies: A Feminist Publication on Art & Politics, Issue 11 (Vol 3, No 3), 1981 (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Exhibition Catalog for 'Recent American Synagogue Architecture,' 6 October to 8 December 1963, The Jewish Museum, New York (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Photocopy of Huron Jackson's 'A Guide to New York Architecture, 1660-1952,' Reinhold Publishing Corporation, 1952. (Box 3, Folder 2)
- Series III: Projects
  - Stable, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Gansevoort Market Area Study, NY, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Fleming-Joffe Ltd., New York and St. Louis, 1967 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Nine-G Cooperative, New York, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Rudolph House, Martha's Vineyard, Massachusetts, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Claremont Gardens, Ossining, NY, 1970s (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Jenings Hall Senior Citizen's Housing, Brooklyn, New York, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - New Goddard-Riverside Apartments, New York, 1984 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Columbus Green Apartments, New York, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chung Pak/Everlasting Pine, New York, 1992 (Box 3, Folder 12)